<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Portfolio on Matthew Montesano</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/</link><description>Recent content in Portfolio on Matthew Montesano</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Papers</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/papers/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 13:18:41 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/papers/</guid><description>As an author: Successful, Easy to Access, Online Publication of COVID-19 Data During the Pandemic, New York City, 2020 Matthew Peter Mannix Montesano MPH, Kimberly Johnson MS, Andrew Tang MPH, Jennifer Sanderson Slutsker MPH, Pui Ying Chan MPH, Kevin Guerra MPH, Jennifer MacGregor BA, Jeffrey Grossman BA, Maura Kennelly MPH, and Corinne N. Thompson PhD, MSc
American Journal of Public Health
COVID-19 Outbreak — New York City, February 29–June 1, 2020 Thompson et al (the COVID-19 Response Team)</description></item><item><title>Talks</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/talks/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 13:18:41 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/talks/</guid><description>Talks I enjoy presenting my work. I like to talk about things like:
What we&amp;rsquo;re doing to make public health data more accessible Why it&amp;rsquo;s important for public health agencies to focus on how they communicate data How to do data communication well: research, practices, and methods Where data visualization, design, web usability, and health comms overlap Specific projects: our research, our problems, our solutions, and our results 2022 &amp;ldquo;Effective Data Communication.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/about/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/about/</guid><description>About me Currently, I am the Director of Data Communication in the Bureau of Environmental Surveillance and Policy at the NYC Department of Health and Mental Hygiene. In this role, I:
Lead work on the Environment &amp;amp; Health Data Portal Conduct user research Create new digital interactive web products In this role, I&amp;rsquo;ve overseen a dramatic expansion of the EH Data Portal, launching a data stories initiative, designing a suite of interactive one-page data applications, and overseeing a major re-design and re-build of our full site.</description></item><item><title>Old work</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/other/old-work/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/other/old-work/</guid><description>Here&amp;rsquo;s some old work.</description></item><item><title>Data Portal Redesign Part 1: Problems and Priorities</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/portal-redesign/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/portal-redesign/</guid><description>In 2021, our team began a re-design of the Environment and Health Data Portal. This site is one of the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s marquee data communication platforms and a major way that our bureau and division communicate.
The old EH Data Portal. The site was designed to store and automatically visualize datasets (&amp;ldquo;indicators&amp;rdquo;) that show how environments and heath are related. Over time, the site grew to include additional content types, like:</description></item><item><title>Other COVID vis</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/covid-vis/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/covid-vis/</guid><description>I spent 27 months activated with the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s COVID-19 response. In addition to working on our agency&amp;rsquo;s data communication, I provided a lot of data visualization support to other areas of the respose, including:
Visualization for agency &amp;ldquo;white papers&amp;rdquo; The agency periodically releases snapshot-reports to highlight some key findings. I contributed data visualization to several of these, including:
Post-vaccination Outcomes. Omicron report. Visualization for the Commissioner&amp;rsquo;s social media Commissioner Chokshi liked data and good data vis, and I was periodically asked to develop visualizations (and sometimes, tweet threads) for him to tweet.</description></item><item><title>COVID-19 data strategy</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/covid-2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/covid-2/</guid><description>I spent 27 months activated with the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s COVID-19 response, working on our data webpages. In this time, I:
Led COVID-19 data visualization and data communication strategy Managed and developed front-end web code Trained and mentored analysts to do similar work Authored and co-authored papers, spoke at conferences and workshops This project had wide-reaching effects.
We built the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s most high-profile digital product ever. We brought our knowledge to the world, allowing it to influence research, policy, and pandemic response We raised the profile of the importance of smart, strategic data communication in the department We advised people in other jurisdictions' health agencies on how to do similar work Here&amp;rsquo;s what we tried to do with our data communication project:</description></item><item><title>COVID-19 data pages</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/covid-19-pages/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/covid-19-pages/</guid><description>I spent 27 months activated with the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s COVID-19 response, working on our data webpages. In this time, I:
Led COVID-19 data visualization and data communication strategy Managed and developed front-end web code Trained and mentored analysts to do similar work Authored and co-authored papers, spoke at conferences and workshops A snip of the COVID-19 data pages. Initial effort In March 2020, after a few days regularly refreshing the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s webpages, I began building a prototype of a COVID-19 data webpage.</description></item><item><title>Automating Updates</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/automating-updates/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 10:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/automating-updates/</guid><description>Heat syndrome My climate colleagues approached me to talk about a page that would provide near realtime data on temperature and heat-related illnesses.
I built a simple page that showed charts with the data. My colleagues wrote an R script to output the files each day, and scheduled a bash script to push the files to the Github repository. The charts were built to read the data in the Github repo.</description></item><item><title>JavaScript Interactives</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/js-interactives/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/js-interactives/</guid><description>Air Quality Explorer In 2019, I was learning about our air quality research team, and what they learn from the NYC Community Air Survey.
I learned that they sample air quality each season from nearly 100 locations around the city, and combine those readings with data on things like building density and emissions, traffic, industrial activity, and more. This lets them create a complex model that can predict air quality in unmonitored areas, based on what they know about all the other underlying factors.</description></item><item><title>Re-designing Neighborhood Reports</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/nrs/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 10:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/nrs/</guid><description>The EH Data Portal&amp;rsquo;s Neighborhood Reports were designed to show data for a neighborhood on a a specific environmental health topic. There are neighborhood reports for Asthma, Outdoor air, Housing, Climate, and Active design. They looked like this, below: a list of indicators, neighborhood-boro-city comparisons, a trend, and a big colorful indicator about whether or not the chosen neighborhood is better, in the middle, or worse than most other neighborhoods.</description></item><item><title>Data Stories</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/data-stories/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/data-stories/</guid><description>In 2019, early in my work on the Environment &amp;amp; Health Data Portal, our team was looking for some novel ways to communicate our data.
The problem Our bureau was full of amazing researchers doing fascinating work. Our EH Data Portal was there to serve them. How could it best shine a light on their work?
Making datasets available is helpful, but the data itself is just the tip of the iceberg about what we know about a topic.</description></item><item><title>Vaccine Communications</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/immz-comms/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/immz-comms/</guid><description>In 2017 and 2018, I was the Communications Lead with the Philadelphia Department of Public Health Immunization Program. In this job, I did the following:
Media campaign I lead development of a large media campaign for adult and childhood immunization campaign: developing strategy, designing billboards, and recording PSAs.
School requirements robocall The school vaccine requirements changed, so over the summer, we had to reach nearly 200,000 public school students' families with info so that their kids could start the school year.</description></item><item><title>Work with Federal Clients</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/federal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/federal/</guid><description>While working with a health communications contractor in 2016 and 2017, I lead work on health communications projects for federal clients.
Healthy People 2020 I lead a team of communicators and developers to maintain and develop HealthyPeople2020. Part of this work included leading design and development of new data communication functions like:
Midcourse Review &amp;times; HP2020 Midcourse Review Close Disparities Widget &amp;times; HP2020 Disparities Widget Close Healthy People 2030 I lead a year-long user-research initiative with dozens of stakeholders to begin strategic planning for the Office of Disease Prevention and Health Promotion&amp;rsquo;s decennial Healthy People initiaive - planning major improvements to services, web usability, and data delivery that would be implemented years later.</description></item><item><title>Minnesota Data Portal</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/minnesota/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/minnesota/</guid><description>From 2013 to 2016, I worked with the Minnesota Department of Health in the Environmental Public Health Tracking Program. I coordinated work on its Data Access Portal, working with epidemiologists, GIS professionals, and developers.
This was my first experience working with web content about public health data, and I had something of a revelation. I reflected on my previous experience as a plain language health writer, and as a nonprofit proposal writer - both of these were about writing so that your audience would do something in response, either change a health behavior, or fund a nonprofit.</description></item></channel></rss>