<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Matthew Montesano</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Matthew Montesano</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 10:14:19 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Automating Updates</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/automating-updates/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 10:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/automating-updates/</guid><description>Heat syndrome My climate colleagues approached me to talk about a page that would provide near realtime data on temperature and heat-related illnesses.
I built a simple page that showed charts with the data. My colleagues automated an R script to output the files and a bash script to push the files to the Github repository. The charts were built to read the data in the Github repo. So, without intervention, this page updates every day.</description></item><item><title>Data Portal Redesign Part 2: The Work</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/portal-redesign-2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/portal-redesign-2/</guid><description>The groundwork The site re-design started as a pilot in 2020, when we began re-building the Neighborhood Reports. First, we conducted a 6-month user research and user-centered design process, during which we conducted a survey, key informant interviews, and co-design sessions.
Then, we engaged a contractor to re-build the Neighborhood Reports. We wound up launching these on our extant site. This build would form the backbone of our full portal re-build.</description></item><item><title>Data Stories</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/data-stories/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/data-stories/</guid><description>In 2019, early in my work on the Environment &amp;amp; Health Data Portal, our team was looking for some novel ways to communicate our data.
The problem Our bureau was full of amazing researchers doing fascinating work. Our EH Data Portal was there to serve them. How could it best shine a light on their work?
Making datasets available is helpful, but the data itself is just the tip of the iceberg about what we know about a topic.</description></item><item><title>JavaScript Interactives</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/js-interactives/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/js-interactives/</guid><description>Air Quality Explorer In 2019, I was learning about our air quality research team, and what they learn from the NYC Community Air Survey.
I learned that they sample air quality each season from nearly 100 locations around the city, and combine those readings with data on things like building density and emissions, traffic, industrial activity, and more. This lets them create a complex model that can predict air quality in unmonitored areas, based on what they know about all the other underlying factors.</description></item><item><title>Data Portal Redesign Part 1: Problems and Priorities</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/portal-redesign/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/portal-redesign/</guid><description>In 2021, our team began a re-design of the Environment and Health Data Portal. This site is one of the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s marquee data communication platforms. The site was designed to store and automatically visualize datasets (&amp;ldquo;indicators&amp;rdquo;) that show how environments and heath are related.
The old EH Data Portal. The portal&amp;rsquo;s original functionality, automatically visualizing a dataset, became called the Data Explorer. Here&amp;#39;s an example. &amp;times; Visualization of an indicator Close</description></item><item><title>COVID-19 data pages: goals and strategies</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/covid-2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/covid-2/</guid><description>I spent 27 months activated with the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s COVID-19 response, working on our data webpages. In this time, I:
Lead COVID-19 data visualization and data communication strategy Managed and developed front-end web code Trained and mentored analysts to do similar work Authored and co-authored papers, spoke at conferences and workshops This project had wide-reaching effects.
We built the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s most high-profile digital product ever. We brought our knowledge to the world, allowing it to influence research, policy, and pandemic response We raised the profile of the importance of smart, strategic data communication in the department We advised people in other jurisdictions' health agencies on how to do similar work Here&amp;rsquo;s what we tried to do with the COVID-19 data pages:</description></item><item><title>COVID-19 data pages: timeline</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/covid-19-pages/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/covid-19-pages/</guid><description>I spent 27 months activated with the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s COVID-19 response, working on our data webpages. In this time, I:
Lead COVID-19 data visualization and data communication strategy Managed and developed front-end web code Trained and mentored analysts to do similar work Authored and co-authored papers, spoke at conferences and workshops This project had wide-reaching effects.
We built the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s most high-profile digital product ever. We brought our knowledge to the world, allowing it to influence research, policy, and pandemic response We raised the profile of the importance of smart, strategic data communication in the department We advised people in other jurisdictions' health agencies on how to do similar work Initial push In March 2020, after a few days regularly refreshing the Health Department&amp;rsquo;s webpages, I began building a prototype of a COVID-19 data webpage.</description></item><item><title>Philadelphia Immunization Program</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/immz-comms/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/immz-comms/</guid><description>In 2017 - 2018, I was the Communications Lead with the Philadelphia Department of Public Health Immunization Program. In this job, I did the following:
Media campaign. I lead development of a large media campaign for adult and childhood immunization campaign: developing strategy, designing billboards, and recording PSAs.
School requirements robocall: The school vaccine requirements changed, so over the summer, we had to reach nearly 200,000 public school students' families with info so that their kids could start the school year.</description></item><item><title>Work with Federal Clients</title><link>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/federal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 12:14:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://mmontesanonyc.github.io/work-portfolio/posts/federal/</guid><description>While working with a health communications contractor, I lead work on health communications projects for federal clients.
Healthy People 2020 I lead a team of communicators and developers to maintain and develop HealthyPeople2020. Part of this work included leading design and development of new data communication functions like:
Midcourse Review &amp;times; HP2020 Midcourse Review Close Disparities Widget &amp;times; HP2020 Disparities Widget Close Healthy People 2030 I lead a year-long user-research initiative with dozens of stakeholders to begin strategic planning for the Office of Disease Prevention and Health Promotion&amp;rsquo;s decennial Healthy People initiaive - planning major improvements to services, web usability, and data delivery that would be implemented years later.</description></item></channel></rss>